<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mystical Babylon availed wherein is proved, I. That Rome-papal is mystical-Babylon, II. That the Pope of Rome is the beast, III. That the Church of Rome is the great whore, IV. That the Roman-priests are the false prophet : also A call to the people of God to come out of Babylon / by Hanserd Knollys ...</title>
            <author>Knollys, Hanserd, 1599?-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 89 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47567</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K718</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17048</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12863232</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12863232</idno>
            <idno type="VID">94701</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47567)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94701)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 718:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mystical Babylon availed wherein is proved, I. That Rome-papal is mystical-Babylon, II. That the Pope of Rome is the beast, III. That the Church of Rome is the great whore, IV. That the Roman-priests are the false prophet : also A call to the people of God to come out of Babylon / by Hanserd Knollys ...</title>
                  <author>Knollys, Hanserd, 1599?-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94701:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>MYSTICAL BABYLON</hi> UNVAILED.</p>
            <p>Wherein is Proved,
<list>
                  <item>I. That <hi>Rome</hi>-Papal is myſtical-Babylon.</item>
                  <item>II. That the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Beaſt.</item>
                  <item>III. That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the great Whore.</item>
                  <item>IV. That the Roman-Prieſts are the falſe Prophet.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>ALSO A CALL To all the People of God To come out of BABYLON.</p>
            <p>By <hi>HANSERD KNOLLYS, a Servant of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſa. 57.14.</hi>
                  </bibl> Take up the ſtumbling-block out of the way of my People.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rev. 18.6.</hi>
                  </bibl> Reward her even as ſhe Rewarded you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:94701:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Iſaiah Thomas</head>
                  <q>NEC ELA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUS NEC DEJEC<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUS</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="epistle_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:94701:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Ingenuous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is an Aſtoniſhment beyond the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of Nature, Reaſon and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that the Papiſts (<hi>eſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> the Prieſts and Jeſuits of the Church of</hi> Rome ſo odious in their bloody Tenents, ſo prodigious in their Helliſh Plots, ſuch inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>crable Incendiaries, and furious Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ns for murdering of Princes, ſhould be ſuffered to increaſe, and indulged to multiply in a Proteſtant Nation, as of late years they have done in this Kingdom. Aſſuredly it could never have been ſo, but that the Lord in his just <hi>Indignation</hi> againſt us for our <hi>God-provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Sins of Atheiſm, Idolatry, Profaneneſs, Adultery, and other heinous wickedneſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends <hi>(and ſuffers us to ripen, and be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for ſome)</hi> dreadful Judgment, which God may juſtly bring upon this Land and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the hand of the Papiſts, if we Repent not of thoſe Abominations, and do not reform
<pb facs="tcp:94701:3"/>
them. It is <hi>more</hi> than Manifeſt by <hi>woful</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that the <hi>main</hi> End of the Papists in all their Plots and Conſpiracies is the <hi>utter</hi> Destruction of the Proteſtants (whom they call <hi>Hereticks</hi>) and the <hi>Proteſtant</hi>-Religion in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land eſpecially,</hi> and the <hi>Re-eſtabliſhment</hi> of the <hi>Popiſh</hi>-Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this Kingdom; which End the Popiſh-Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants in <hi>England (in this Bloody and Traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous deſign, that Damnable and Helliſh Plot contrived and carried on by them for Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Murdering the King, Subverting the Government, and for Rooting out and Deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Proteſtant-Religion, as the King and Parliament have voted and declared)</hi> are ſtill endeavouring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> effect, and bring to paſs. The concurrent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our <hi>grand</hi> and greatest Enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the World durſt not entertain a <hi>Thought</hi> of <hi>Invaſion,</hi> did they not Hope, <hi>(when Time ſerves)</hi> to find amongſt us a <hi>Side</hi> and <hi>Faction</hi> of numerous and <hi>Seditious</hi> Papiſts to joyn, with them. Were we rid of the Papiſts, and were Idolatry, Atheiſm, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Blaſphemy put away, as in Policy, Reaſon, and Religion theſe ought to be, The <hi>Royal</hi> Perſon of the King would be ſafe from Aſſaſſination, and the Government ſecure from Subverſion. And the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant-Religion free from utter Destruction, by the bleſſed Protection of Almighty God. Conformity unto all <hi>Oaths, Teſts,</hi> and outward formal <hi>Satisfactions</hi> of State, concurring with a full</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94701:3"/>
            <head>Myſtical-Babylon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nvailed.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The Method that I have choſen to Unvail</hi> Myſtical-Babylon, <hi>is, by proving theſe</hi> four <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> viz.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> That Rome-Papal is Myſtical-Babylon.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> That the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Beaſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the great Whore.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> That the Roman-Prieſts are the falſe Prophet.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Propoſition I.</hi> That Rome-Papal is Myſtical-Babylon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Aſtern <hi>Babylon</hi> of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> in <hi>Chaldaea,</hi> was a famous City, Called the <hi>Lady</hi> of Kingdoms<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iſa. 47.1, 5.</note> and the <hi>glory</hi> of Kingdoms<note n="(b)" place="margin">Iſa. 13.19.</note> under whoſe Kings the People of God were Captivated and oppreſſed violently<note n="(c)" place="margin">2 Chron. 36.14,-20. and Jer. 51.34, 35.</note>. For which violence done to <hi>Zion,</hi> and other God-provoking Sins, that great City and Kingdom was deſtroyed by <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 45.1-4 and 47.1-9.</note> whom God raiſed up to execute his righteous Judgments upon them for their Iniquities, lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> before
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94701:4"/>
Saint <hi>John</hi>'s time. Therefore <hi>Myſterie, Babylon</hi> the great, (ſo Named, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.5.) is ſome other great City, which doth reſemble <hi>Old-Babylon</hi> for Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5.47. Perſecution, <hi>Lam.</hi> 5.1.5. Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 51.25. Oppreſſion, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 50.33. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.4. and Pride, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.1, 5, 7. <hi>And thou ſaidſt, I ſhall be a Lady for ever, —I am, and none elſe beſides me.</hi> And ſo doth <hi>Myſtical-Babylon</hi> ſay in her Heart, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18 7. <hi>I ſit a Queen.</hi> Alſo Blood-guiltineſs, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 79.1, 2, 3. <hi>The blood of thy Servants have they ſhed</hi> like Water round about <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and ſo doth Myſtical-Babylon, <hi>Revel.</hi> 26.6. <hi>For they have ſhed the Blood of Saints and Prophets, Rev.</hi> 18.24. As the City <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was <hi>Spiritually called Sodom and Aegypt,</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Rev. 11.8.</note> 
                  <hi>where our Lord was cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> So <hi>Rome Pagan</hi> and <hi>Papal</hi> is <hi>Myſtically</hi> called <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> where the Saints have been and ſhall be killed,<note n="(f)" place="margin">Rev. 6.9, 10, 11. Rev. 11.7.16, 6. Rev. 18.13, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>And in her was found the Blood of Prophets and</hi> of Saints, and of all that were ſlain upon the Earth. That which Jeſus Chriſt <hi>revealed</hi> by his <hi>Angel</hi> unto his Servant <hi>John</hi> touching <hi>Myſtical-Babylon</hi> in this <hi>Prophecy</hi> of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> can agree to no other City but <hi>Rome</hi> only. For <hi>firſt,</hi> No other City (in Saint <hi>John</hi>'s time) was built upon <hi>Seven</hi> Mountains, or Hills, but <hi>Rome</hi> only, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.5, 8, 9, 18. <hi>And the ſeven Heads are ſeven Mountains on which the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Sitteth,</hi> called <hi>the great City,</hi> verſe 18. <hi>whoſe Name is Myſterie Babylon the great,</hi> verſe 5. So <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertius,</hi>
                  <note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Propert. Eleg. 10. l. 3.</hi> Septem urbs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Jugis toti quae praeſidet Orbi.</note> 
                  <hi>Virgil,</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Virgil. Georg. 2.</hi> ω. Pulcherrima Roma, Septem quae una ſibi Muro circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dedit arces. <hi>Ovid. 1. de Triſtibus l. 3. Elog. 7.</hi> Dum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſuis victrix ſeptem de Montibus Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem Proſpiciet domitum, Martia Roma Legar.</note> 
                  <hi>Ovid, (i) Cornel. à Lap.</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">Cornel. à Lap. in Apoc. 17.3, 9. <hi>In ſeptem Montibus patet denotari</hi> Romam.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarm.</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Bellar. <hi>de</hi> R. P. l. 2. c. 2. &amp; l. 3. c. 12.</note> So do <hi>Viegas, Suarez, Ribera,</hi> and divers others affirm, <hi>That by Babylon in the Book of the Revelation Rome is Figured forth.</hi> And the <hi>Remiſts</hi> in their Teſtament acknowledge, <hi>That by Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon is meant Rome:</hi> See their Notes on 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.13. and upon the 17. and 18. Chapters of the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94701:4"/>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> No other City in the World had ſeven Kings, that is, Seven ſeveral Kinds of Governours ſucceeding one another, but <hi>Rome</hi> only, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.10. <hi>And there are ſeven Kings, five are fallen, and one is, and the other is not yet come.</hi> The <hi>five Kings,</hi> that were fallen, paſt and gone before <hi>John</hi>'s time, are men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by <hi>Tit. Livius,</hi> l. 6. What the <hi>Romans</hi> did (ſaith <hi>Livy,</hi>) under their Kings, and after under their Conſuls, Dictators, Decemvirs, and Conſular-Tribunes, whither as to Wars abroad, or ſuppreſſing Troubles at home, I have ſet forth in five Books. <hi>And this</hi> One is<note n="(m)" place="margin">Rev. 17.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> the Emperour, for the Caeſars were the the ſixth Head of <hi>Rome,</hi> who Reigned in St. <hi>John</hi>'s time; <hi>The other is not yet come, viz.</hi> the <hi>Seventh</hi> Head of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Seventh King, or Kind of <hi>Roman</hi>-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, <hi>to wit,</hi> the Popes of <hi>Rome, Revel.</hi> 17.11. <hi>And HE</hi> (that is, <hi>the POPE) is of the Seven, and goeth into Perdition.</hi> This <hi>Seventh</hi> Kind of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the <hi>Roman</hi>-Kingdom by Popes was not come in Saint <hi>John</hi>'s Time. So then it is manifeſt, that <hi>Rome</hi> is the City, which had ſeven Kings, Heads, or Kinds of Governours, that ſucceeded one another; Now let any One ſhew us another City that hath had ſeven Kings, or ſeveral Kinds of Governours <hi>[Et erit mihi magnus Apollo]</hi> And let him be Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> No other City in Saint <hi>John's</hi> time did Reign over the Kings of the Earth, but <hi>Rome</hi> only, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.18. <hi>And the Woman which thou ſaweſt</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>is that City the Great</hi> (verſe 5. My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, Babylon the Great, <hi>viz.</hi> Rome) <hi>which Reigneth over the Kings of the Earth.</hi> Yea, it is very evident by the Teſtimony and Confeſſion of many Popiſh-Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, who for their Learning, <hi>(and Dignity in the Church of Rome)</hi> were Eminent, <hi>That Rome is that great City,</hi> which by the Emperours <hi>Authority</hi> in Saint <hi>John</hi>'s time, and by the Pope's <hi>Power</hi> ſince, hath Reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſtill Reigneth over the Kings of the Earth.<note n="(n)" place="margin">Bellarm. lib. 3. de Pont. R. c. 13. <hi>Per Meretricem intelligi</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſaith, <hi>That Rome is to be underſtood by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94701:5"/>
the great Whore.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Poole</hi>
                  <note n="(o)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Polus Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal.</hi> de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio. <hi>p. 91. Petri</hi> Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dram ſuper om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia Imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Solia, &amp; omnia Regum tribunalia Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituit Chriſtus.</note> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt hath ſet Peter's Chair above all the Thrones of Emperours, and above all the Tribunals of Kings,</hi> [But Chriſt did not ſit in any ſuch Chair of <hi>Kingly</hi> State <hi>as the Pope doth;</hi> nor did Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> nor any of Chriſt's Apoſtles, no not Saint <hi>Paul (the chiefeſt of all the Apoſtles,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.5. and 12.11.]<note n="(p)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſodorus Muſconius</hi> de Majeſtate Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Milit. <hi>l. 1. c. 7. p. 26. Venetiis,</hi> anno <hi>1602.</hi> Pontifex <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus</hi> eſt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, Rex Regum, &amp; Dominus Dominantium. <hi>Abra. Bzovius</hi> de Pont. <hi>Rom.</hi> Coloniae <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grip. 1619. ſays,</hi> Papa eſt Chriſtianorum Monarcha, Mortalium Supremus, Judex Coeli, Arbiter Orbis, <hi>cap. 1.3, 16, 32, 45. Celſus Mancinus,</hi> de Juribus Principatuum <hi>Romae 1596. lib. 3. cap. 1, 2, &amp;c. ſaith,</hi> Papa eſt totius Orbis Dominus: Poteſtas Papae tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralis eſt omnium aliarum Poteſtatum eminentiſſima, Aliae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Poteſtates omnes ab illo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſodorus Muſconius</hi> ſaith, That the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Univerſal Judge; HE is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords. <hi>However,</hi> That Teſtimony recorded, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. is undeniable. <hi>And it came to paſs in thoſe Days, that there went out a DECREE from Caeſar Auguſtus</hi> (the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour) <hi>that all the World ſhould be Taxed.</hi> From what hath been Confeſſed and Teſtified by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves, it is plain and evident, <hi>That Rome-Papal is Myſtical-Babylon</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Viegas</hi> in <hi>Apoc. 17.</hi> Com. <hi>1.</hi> S. <hi>3.</hi> Inquit, Nomine <hi>Babilonis</hi> urbem <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam</hi> ſignificari in hoc <hi>Apocalypſis</hi> opere; ubi toties <hi>Babilon</hi> nominatur. vid. <hi>Oroſium</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Hiſt. <hi>Par.</hi> in <hi>Apoc. 14.8.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94701:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Propoſition II.</hi> That the POPE of <hi>Rome</hi> is the BEAST.</head>
               <p>THe great Monarchs and Monarchies of this World have been Figured forth by Beaſts of Prey. God ſhewed his Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> the <hi>four</hi> great Kingdoms of this World, <hi>viz.</hi> the Aſſyrio-Caldean, the Medi-Perſian, the Grecian, and the Roman Kingdoms by a Viſion of <hi>four</hi> Ravenous and devouring Beaſts, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.3, 4.—8.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Dan. 7.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>And behold a fourth Beaſt</hi> (the Roman-Kings and Kingdoms with ſeven Heads, and ten Horns, and upon the Horns ten Crowns; And upon his <hi>ſeventh</hi> Head <hi>two</hi> Horns, like a Lamb; <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.1.11.) <hi>dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and terrible,</hi> &amp;c. ver. 7. <hi>Exceedingly, And divers from all the other three Beaſts.</hi> And Jeſus Chriſt ſhewed his Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> the ſame <hi>fourth</hi> Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. <hi>And the Beaſt that I ſaw, was like unto a Leopard, and his Feet were as the Feet of a Bear, and his mouth as the mouth of a Lyon, And the Dragon</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">That old Serpent, the Devil and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, For the Devil and the Pope are alike <hi>(as Father and Son)</hi> in many Things: The Devil contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted Gods word, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.4. So doth the Pope 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. forbidding to Marry. This confeſſeth Chriſt, <hi>Mark.</hi> 3.11. but denies his Laws; So doth the Pope, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11, 15, 16, 17. The Devil would be worſhipped as God, <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.6. The Pope would be Exalted above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>gave him his Power, his Throne, and great Authority; And he ſpake as the Dragon,</hi> ver. 11. The moſt full Deſcription of the Roman-Papal Beaſt is <hi>expreſly</hi> written in the 17. <hi>Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Revelation. And the Angel ſaid unto me,</hi> ver. 7. <hi>I will tell thee the Myſtery of the Woman, and of the Beaſt,</hi> &amp;c. This BEAST the Angel deſcribed unto St. <hi>John</hi> in three particulars <hi>(which can agree with no other Perſons, Powers, Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94701:6"/>
Kings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Devil challengeth to be the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of all King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the Earth, <hi>Luke</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7. So doth the Pope of <hi>Rome, vid. Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>de Pont. Rom.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>nor Dominion in the World but the Popes of</hi> Rome <hi>only.) Firſt,</hi> by his Paſt, Preſent, and Future State, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>The Beaſt that Was, and Is not, and yet IS. Secondly,</hi> by his twofold Number, <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>HE is the Eight, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Seven. Thirdly,</hi> by his Riſe and Ruine, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. &amp; 11. <hi>The Beaſt ſhall aſcend out of the bottomleſs Pit, and go into Perdition:</hi> That lawleſs One the Son of Perdition, <hi>and goeth into Perdition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Beaſt is deſcribed by his PAST State, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.8. <hi>The Beaſt which thou Saweſt, WAS, and is not;</hi> that is to ſay, The Roman <hi>State</hi> and Kingdom was <hi>formerly,</hi> and even in St. <hi>John's</hi> Time, what it is not, now in our Time, in divers Reſpects, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Kingdom was then a Power ordained of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.7. unto which Roman-Power our bleſſed Saviour Jeſus Chriſt being then in the Form of a Servant, Phil. 2.7.8. <hi>was obedient to Death.</hi> So were Chriſts Diſciples, and the <hi>Primitive</hi> Chriſtians, Search thoſe Scriptures<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <p>Mar. 12.17. Acts. 25.10.11. 1 Pet. 2.13, 14, 15. Tit. 3.1. Not only <hi>Paul,</hi> but <hi>Peter,</hi> and Chriſt himſelf was Subject to the Roman-Pagan Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings, and Governors. But the <hi>Beaſt of the eighth</hi> Head the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> will be the Supreme Power over all Kings &amp; King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In Bella Coenae Dom.</hi> Sect. 3, 4, 5. againſt Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and all Hereticks, vid. <hi>Remonſtran. Hibernorum per</hi> R. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. part. 1. cap. 3. Sect. 4. pag. 7.</p>
                  </note>. The Roman Powers though <hi>Pagan</hi> Perſecutors of Chriſt and Chriſtians WAS Gods Ordinance of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, until the Ten Kings gave the Beaſt <hi>(the Pope of Rome)</hi> his Power, his Throne and great Authority. <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.2. And then the Angel told St. <hi>John; HE is not; viz.</hi> The Beaſt of the ſeventh and eighth Head is not Gods Ordinance of Magiſtracy; nor a Power ordained of God. Here let it be <hi>Seriouſly</hi> conſidered, That the <hi>Dragon,</hi> which gave the <hi>Beaſt</hi> his Power, Throne, and great Authority, Was not the Roman-Pagan-Emperours, for they never gave their Power and great Authority unto the Beaſt of the ſeventh and eighth Head, <hi>viz. the Pope of Rome.</hi> The Roman-Heathen, yea and Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours ſtood in the Popes Way, and did let and hinder his Riſe, and Reigning Power, until they were Removed out of his Way, as was foretold by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2, 3, 4, 7, 8, 9, 10. And thus it came to paſs; <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great leaving <hi>Rome,</hi> and making <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:94701:6"/>
the <hi>Imperial</hi> Seat, thereby <hi>(ſede vacante)</hi> the then Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> got full Poſſeſſion of that City; And ſo the Chief Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> continued his <hi>Primacy</hi> from that Time until <hi>(at laſt)</hi> the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Empire determined in <hi>Auguſtulus</hi> anno 475. or thereabouts; And about the year 607. the then Biſhop of <hi>Rome, Boniface</hi> the III. obtained from <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperour of the Eaſt, <hi>That not the Patriarch of Conſtantinople but the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>be univerſal-Biſhop.</hi> But for all this Riſe and Advance,<note place="margin">Avent. Annal. Boyor. lib. 5. and pag. 447. and lib. 9.</note> The Beaſt of the eighth Head, (<hi>the Pope of</hi> Rome) IS NOT of the <hi>Seven, that is to ſay,</hi> HE is not <hi>Supreme</hi> as the Roman Emperours were. For although the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours aſſumed the Title of <hi>Pontifex Maximus</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dionyſ. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licarnaſ. Ant. Rom.</hi> 12. And <hi>Godwin</hi>'s An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiq. l. 2. Sect. 2. cap. 15.</note> and added it to the <hi>Imperial</hi> Crown; yet the Imperial Crown of the <hi>Roman</hi> Government and <hi>Kingdom</hi> was not added to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Petra dedit Petro, Petrus Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adema Rodulpho.</hi> Bellar. de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. lib. 2. cap. l. 2. c. 17.</note> until <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. <hi>(Emperour),</hi> whom <hi>Gregory</hi> the VII. Excommunicated and Depoſed, and Made <hi>Rodulphus</hi> Emperour in his ſtead: And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards when <hi>Henry</hi> the V. came to <hi>Rome</hi> to be Crowned by Pope <hi>Paſcal.</hi> II. The Pope would not conſent to his Coronation, <hi>untill the Emperour did give over all Right of Election of</hi> Popes, <hi>and of Inveſtures of</hi> Biſhops <hi>by Staff and Ring.</hi> And thus the Pope gained the Power of <hi>Temporal Soveraignty,</hi> and ſo <hi>IS of the Seven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor did all this Epiſcopal, Pontificial, and Imperial Dignity, Power, and Authority fill and ſatisfie the <hi>Beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Pope of Rome,</hi> until he obtained Supremacy above all <hi>general</hi> Councils<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellarmine</hi> boaſteth ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, The laſt <hi>Lateran</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil under <hi>Leo</hi> 10th. <hi>expreſly</hi> and <hi>profeſſedly</hi> teacheth, That the Pope is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, <hi>Bellar. de Concil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</note>, And ſo the <hi>Pope</hi> became <hi>Pontifex Maximus,</hi> the chief high Prieſt, who tranſlated Kings and Emperours at his Pleaſure. <hi>Bellarmine</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">Bellar de tranſ. Imp. Rom. in tribus libris, per Epiſcopi Rom. authoritatem.</note> ſaith, The Roman Empire was by the Authority of the Pope, tranſlated from the <hi>Graecians</hi> to the <hi>French,</hi> and from <hi>Charles</hi> the Great and the <hi>French</hi> unto the Family of <hi>Otho</hi> and the <hi>Saxons,</hi> which is now the Roman Papal Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> with its ſeven Electors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Roman Beaſt alſo <hi>(that WAS)</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by his <hi>Preſent</hi> State, 1. <hi>Negatively,</hi> And is NOT.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94701:7"/>
2. <hi>Affirmatively,</hi> And yet IS<note n="(i)" place="margin">Rev. 17.8, 9.</note>. Herein lyeth another Myſtery; <hi>And here is the Mind, that hath Wiſdom:</hi> to know in what Reſpect the Roman Beaſt is NOT, and yet IS. I will not be poſitive, nor dare I preſume to make a <hi>determinate</hi> Judgment, and to give a Reſolution herein; but I humbly offer my Opinion, and ſubmit it to the Mind, that hath Wiſdom, and let him, that hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in this Myſtery, judge what I ſay. It is ſaid HE is NOT, with Reſpect to thoſe five Kings, or Kinds of Kingly Government, <hi>viz.</hi> Kings, Conſuls, Dictators, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemvirs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ancients.</hi> Irenaeus, l. <hi>5.</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus Haereſ. c. <hi>28.</hi> Tertul. de Reſur. car. c. <hi>25.</hi> Ander. Caeſar. Epiſc. cap. <hi>36.</hi> in Apoc. <hi>13.</hi> v. <hi>1.</hi> Beda in Apoc. <hi>13.</hi> v. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> and Tribunes, which were fallen, <hi>that</hi> is, paſt and gone before St. <hi>John</hi>'s time. For this BEAST, which roſe out of the Sea of the Troubles and Confuſions in <hi>Rome,</hi> and in the Roman Empire, and out of the Earth of the Apoſtacies<note n="(k)" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1, 2, 3. and 2 Theſ. 2.3, 4, 5.</note> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> foretold ſhould be in the latter Days, and which the Angel was now Revealing unto <hi>John</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">Rev. 13.1. and ver. 11. and Rev. 17.3.7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> Papal Rome, <hi>Is NOT yet Come,</hi> Rev. 17.10. <hi>that is,</hi> HE was not in Being, when St. <hi>John</hi> write this Book. And yet HE IS, <hi>that is to ſay</hi> ONE IS,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Modern.</hi> Joan. Viguer. Inſtit. Theol. c. <hi>21.</hi> Sect. <hi>3.</hi> v. <hi>4.</hi> Nich. Sander. l. <hi>8.</hi> de viſib. Eccl. Monarch. c. <hi>1.</hi> in Libro octavo. Nich. Zegar in Apoc. <hi>13.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>to wit</hi> the Emperour, who IS the <hi>ſixth</hi> King, then in Being in St. <hi>John</hi>'s time, and ſometime after, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.10. <hi>And there are ſeven Kings, Five are fallen, And ONE IS, And the Other is not yet come,</hi> viz. to be the <hi>Seventh</hi> head of the Roman Empire, and the Supreme Governour of the Roman Monarchy. The Roman-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal BEAST is NOT, <hi>that is to ſay,</hi> HE is not God's Ordinance of Magiſtracy, nor a lawful Power ordained of God, but he IS an Uſurper of the Roman Kingdom; And an Inſtrument of the great Dragon,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Benedict. Pere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius, l. <hi>14.</hi> in Dan. R. Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus l. <hi>3.</hi> de R. P. c. <hi>2.8.</hi> Franciſ. Rib. in Apoc. <hi>13.</hi> Sect. <hi>1.</hi> Hiomne Beſtiam Apoc. <hi>13.1.</hi> ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſimum eſſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>retantur.</note> that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, called the Devil and Satan, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.3.9. <hi>viz.</hi> The Roman Pagan Emperour, And alſo the Dragon, <hi>that old Serpent, which is the Devil, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad Satan,</hi> Rev. 20.2. <hi>viz.</hi> He <hi>that beguiled</hi> Eve, <hi>through his Subtilty,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.3. gave the BEAST his Power, and his Throne and his Supreme Authority. So that Beaſt (<hi>the Pope of</hi> Rome) hath the Roman-Power, but not <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> HE IS NOT, by God's Approbation. And yet HE IS the Supreme Roman-Governour. Yea HE IS of the Seven,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94701:7"/>
                  <hi>to wit,</hi> the ſeventh <hi>King</hi> or <hi>kind</hi> of Kingly Government, <hi>as is before ſaid. And HE even he is the Eighth.</hi> Rev. 17.11.<note n="(m)" place="margin">Beſtia ſc. Papa Rom. Is octavus eſt, Et de ſeptem illis eſt, Quia nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Papa ſc. Antichriſtus (Cornu illud parvulum <hi>Dan. 7.20.</hi>) oriturus erat de medio Cornuum quartae beſtiae, quae Imperium adumbrabat Romanum, <hi>&amp;c. J.W. lib. de ultimo Romae Exitio. p. 6.</hi>
                  </note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Roman BEAST is deſcribed by his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture State: <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.10. <hi>And the other is not yet Come, that is to ſay,</hi> the other King or Kind of Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>viz.</hi> Popes had not gotten the Supreme Power, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Political, nor Eccleſiaſtical. But this Beaſt, that was to Come, <hi>that is,</hi> to ſucceed the Emperours, <hi>was the Popes,</hi> and they are the <hi>Eight</hi> and of the <hi>Seven.</hi> Rev. 17.11. Which will be made appear in the <hi>ſecond</hi> Particular of the Angels <hi>Deſcription</hi> of the BEAST by his <hi>twofold</hi> Number.</p>
               <p>The Second particular, or Part of the Angels Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Roman Beaſt is by his <hi>twofold</hi> Number, <hi>Seven</hi> and <hi>Eight,</hi> The Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> is of the <hi>Seven,</hi> or the <hi>Seventh</hi> King, or <hi>Kingly</hi> kind of Government with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his <hi>Imperial,</hi> or <hi>Magiſterial</hi> Power<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra. Barcl. c. 5.</hi> Non ſolùm in Spiritualibus quoque Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore &amp; Rege major eſt Papa, ſed etiam in temporalibus.</note> over Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours and Kings of the Roman-Kingdom; And HE IS the EIGHT with Reſpect of his <hi>Hierarchical,</hi> or <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical</hi>-Power<note n="(o)" place="margin">
                     <p>Oriohou. in Chymer; 10 l. 97 <hi>Quanto creatura Deo, tanto Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratoria Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtas eſt Papae inferior.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Pope is the ſeventh Head in Nature and Kind: and an Eight alſo in Degree and Power. <hi>Hen. Biſh.</hi> of <hi>Meath,</hi> of Antichriſt. pag. 11.</p>
                  </note> or Principality, which was alſo <hi>there</hi> before, <hi>under former Roman-Governments;</hi> For as to matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> the Romans had of <hi>old</hi> Inſtituted by <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> their <hi>Pontifices</hi> or <hi>under-Prieſts</hi> and over them a Chief Prieſt called <hi>Pontifex Maximus, which lower Prieſts were exempted from civil Juriſdiction, and only Ordered and Governed by him, who was their Pontifex Maximus, HE himſelf not being accountable</hi> to any<note n="(p)" place="margin">Dionyſ. Halicarnaſs Ant. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi>'s Antiq. lib. 2. Sect. 2. cap. 15.</note>. And therefore the Pope is ſaid to be of the SEVEN with Reſpect of his <hi>Imperial</hi> and <hi>Pontifical</hi> Power, unto which HE hath Advanced himſelf in his Dominion and Titles above all Principalities and Powers on Earth, <hi>(no Kings
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94701:8"/>
nor Emperours being excepted or exempted)</hi>
                  <note n="(q)" place="margin">Triplex im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium habet Papa, in terra, in coelo, &amp; (ubi Chirſtus nullum habit) in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorio, in cujus ſignum Tiara Papalis triplici coronâ ornata eſt. <hi>Caeremon. l. 1. Sect. 5 c. 9. &amp; Sect. 7. f. 78. Hab. 3.4. and Zech. 1.18.21.</hi>
                  </note>. And ſo in his exalted Power of <hi>Imperial</hi> and <hi>Pontificial</hi> Horns the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> became the BEAST of the <hi>Eighth</hi> Head <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.11. Who did Riſe out of the Earth having <hi>two Horus</hi> like a Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.11. Horns do ſignifie Power in the Propheſies of the Holy Scripture of Truth, as in <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.20, 21, 22, 23, 24.<note n="(r)" place="margin">
                     <p>Purgatorium eſt peculium Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae, <hi>ſaith</hi> Angelus Pariſienſis.</p>
                     <p>Antoninus part. <hi>3.</hi> tit. <hi>22.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> Sect. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>7.</hi> Bal. in vita Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis <hi>10.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Patres concil. Lateran. Seſſ. <hi>10.</hi> in Orat. Steph. Patra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſis.</p>
                  </note>. So that the <hi>two</hi> Horns of that Beaſt (<hi>the Pope of</hi> Rome) ſignifie his <hi>two</hi> fold Power <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> or <hi>Imperial</hi> and <hi>Pontifical</hi> twiſted and united together in his <hi>Seventh</hi> and <hi>Eighth</hi> Headſhip, For even <hi>HE is the Eight, and is of the Seven,</hi> Rev. 17.11. This Number of the BEAST <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Seventh</hi> and <hi>Eighth</hi> can agree with none of the <hi>Roman</hi> Heads, but Popes <hi>only.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>third</hi> Particular, or Part of the Angels Deſcription of the Roman-Papal-BEAST of the <hi>Seventh</hi> and <hi>Eighth</hi> Head is by his RISE and RUINE, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.8, 11. <hi>The BEAST ſhall aſcend out of the Bottomleſs Pit, and go into Perdition,</hi> ver. 11. <hi>And goeth into Perdition.</hi> I ſhall here ſhew <hi>briefly, firſt</hi> his <hi>Riſe, then</hi> his <hi>Ruine.</hi> Whereby it will more plainly appear, <hi>That the Pope of</hi> Rome <hi>is the BEAST.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> as to the <hi>Riſe</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> of the <hi>Seventh</hi> and <hi>Eight</hi> Head, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Pope of Rome;</hi> we find in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Hiſtories, That <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great changed the Seat of the Emperour from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by leaving <hi>the City of</hi> Rome, as it were vacant. After his Death the <hi>Roman-Empire</hi> was divided, and the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man-Eagle</hi> having <hi>two</hi> great Wings ſpread her ſelf into the Eaſtern and Weſtern Empires; At laſt about <hi>anno</hi> 475. the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Empire quite expired in <hi>Auguſtulus</hi>
                  <note n="(s)" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ambroſe, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, Theophylact</hi> upon 2 Theſ. 2.6, 7.</p>
                     <p>When the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Empire ſhall be taken out of the Way, then ſhall <hi>Antichriſt</hi> Come.</p>
                  </note>. For the Empire having been invaded by the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> and other <hi>barbarous</hi> Nations, by whom alſo <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf was taken and poſſeſſed about <hi>fifty</hi> years, The Pope or Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> himſelf being alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled out the City of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.6, 7. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</note> and put to ſeek <hi>(for a Time)</hi> another Place of abode. About the year 607. <hi>Boniface</hi> III.<note n="(t)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prideaux</hi> Introduction of Hiſtories, Interval. 7. Sect. pag. 89.</note> then <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> obtained from <hi>Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94701:8"/>
then Emperour of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> That not the <hi>Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Conſtanſtinople,</hi> but the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Biſhop.</hi> And now was the <hi>Title</hi> of <hi>Pope</hi> appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which was before communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to other Patriarchs and Biſhops alſo indifferently. After this Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> VII. contended with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth, whom he excommunicated and depoſed, and gave the <hi>Imperial</hi> Crown to <hi>Rodulphus</hi>
                  <note n="(u)" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Petra dedit Petro, Petrus,</hi> DIADEMA <hi>Rodulpho</hi> Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm. de Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. lib. 2. cap. 17.</p>
                     <p>2 Theſ. 2.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>Numen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note>, with this verſe. The Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> being now <hi>Riſen</hi> above all Biſhops Patriarchs and Emperours, HE ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced himſelf above all <hi>general</hi> Councils, which Riſe was fully attained by <hi>Pope Leo</hi> X. as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> boaſteth. The Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> having aſcended thus <hi>high,</hi> HE was <hi>Ambitious</hi> to <hi>Riſe</hi> yet <hi>Higher.</hi> That ſo he might appear to be <hi>That Man of Sin, and Son of Perdition, who oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and exalteth himſelf above every one called God, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Power,</hi> So that <hi>HE as God might ſit in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God.</hi> And to that End the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> confirmed thoſe erroneous Doctrines, and Poſitions of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and cauſed them to be Concluded and Decreed for Doctrines and Articles of Faith, in the general Councils of <hi>Conſtance, Lateran,</hi> and of <hi>Trent. Chriſtophorus Mercellus</hi> ſpeaking to Pope <hi>Julius</hi> II. in the Council of <hi>Lateran,</hi> ſaid<note n="(w)" place="margin">Tu es alter Deus in Terra. Extra. <hi>Joh. 22.</hi> de verb. ſignif. cap. cum interp. <hi>&amp; lib. cerem. 1. Sect. 1. fol. 16.</hi> Eberhardus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. Salisbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſis Impreſſ. Lugd. Anno. <hi>1555.</hi> Edit. nov. Ant. Papae Greg. <hi>13.</hi> Credere Dominum Deum noſtrum Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam non ſic potuiſſe Statuere, prout Statuit, haereticum Cenſeatur.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou art another God upon Earth.</hi> And in the Gloſs on the Canon Law HE is called, <hi>Our Lord God the Pope</hi> by the Popes allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as alſo <hi>divine</hi> Adoration<note n="(x)" place="margin">Thoſe words, <hi>All that is called God, and worſhipped,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.4. are not to be interpreted <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Prelates and Prieſts, but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Objects of divine worſhip, So the <hi>Athenian</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Acts 17.23. were their Idols and Modes of Devotion, and divine Worſhip. So Dan. 11.36.37.40.</note>.</p>
               <p>The Pope of <hi>Rome, the BEAST of the Seventh and Eighth Head,</hi> having aſcended out of the deep Abyſs, or Bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Pit, and Riſen <hi>at laſt</hi> unto this Hight of Impiety; He
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94701:9"/>
having overcome the Saints of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.7. and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>two</hi> Prophetical Witneſſes of Chriſt <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.7. muſt go into Perdition; <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.8, 11. <hi>and goeth into Perdition:</hi> which implies his <hi>gradual</hi> Ruine, ſtep by ſtep. As HE did riſe gradually to the <hi>hight</hi> of his <hi>Grandeur,</hi> ſo HE muſt fall by degrees into <hi>Perdition.</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.8. <hi>Whom the Lord ſhall Conſume with the Spirit of his Mouth,</hi> and <hi>ſhall deſtroy with the Brightneſs of his Coming.</hi> So that this BEAST, (<hi>the Pope of</hi> Rome) ſhall be <hi>firſt</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, and afterwards Deſtroyed, <hi>as is foretold,</hi> Dan. 7.11, 12, 13. Now to be conſumed is to decay, to wax weak, and by ſome Sickneſs or Diſtempers to waſte, pine, and wear away, and at laſt to dye: even ſo ſhall the BEAST, that Man of SIN, the Son of Perdition, <hi>the Pope of</hi> Rome. Who hath been Conſuming many years by the Spirit of Chriſts mouth, <hi>viz.</hi> The powerful and ſpiritual Preaching of the Goſpel of free Grace: by the <hi>Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> witneſſes of Chriſt, his godly and faithful Miniſters. <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Confeſſion is a full Confirmation of the <hi>Popes</hi> Conſumption, his words in Engliſh are theſe—<hi>The Roman See hath by little and little decayed,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="(x)" place="margin">Bellarm. de Rom. Pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>if. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi> Scrip. <hi>1577.</hi>
                  </note>. And it hath much more decayed, and been conſumed ſince that Time, by the Preaching of the Goſpel, through the powerful operation of the holy Spirit<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Rich. Bernar</hi>'s Key of Knowledge, part. 4. pag. 126, 127, 128, 129. Since 1558. <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> the Pope hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Increaſed upon us, But we by Gods power have prevailed againſt him. Have not the Papiſts had ill Succeſs in all their Attempts againſt us? And in ſpite of their Policy, Trecheries, and Treaſons, — we ſtand and they fall; and ſo muſt they now <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> continually, for by an Oath of God it is confirmed unto us, Chap. 10. 5, 6. <hi>That there ſhould be Time no longer.</hi> Read pag. 127, 128. &amp; 129.</note>.</p>
               <p>The utter downfal, and Deſtruction of the Roman Beaſt <hi>(the Pope)</hi> is alſo Propheſied, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.8. <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen, that great City,</hi> (which is <hi>Rome</hi> as hath been fully proved). Alſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.2, 8, 10, 19, 21. <hi>Therefore ſhall her Plagues come in one Day—and ſhe ſhall be utterly burnt with Fire, for ſtrong is the Lord God, who judgeth her. Alas, alas! that great City Babylon</hi> (that is <hi>Rome-papal)
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:94701:9"/>
that mighty City, for in one Hour is thy Judgment come;</hi> and ver. 19. <hi>Alas alas! that great City</hi> (Rome) <hi>for in one hour ſhe is made deſolate.</hi> And <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.19, 20— <hi>And the BEAST,</hi> (that is the Pope of <hi>Rome) was taken, and with him the falſe Prophet—Theſe both were caſt alive into the Lake burning with Brimſtone.</hi> Then ſhall <hi>Rome</hi>-Papal be found no more at all, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.21. and Then ſhall the <hi>Beaſt, (who is the Pope of Rome)</hi> be tormented day and night, for ever and ever, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>
                  <hi>Propoſition III.</hi> That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the great WHORE.</head>
               <p>THE Church of God under the Law was Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by the Prophet<note n="(a)" place="margin"> </note> unto a comely and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate Woman. And the Church of Chriſt under the Goſpel was Revealed to the Apoſtle<note n="(b)" place="margin">Rev. 12.1.</note> by the Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of a <hi>Woman</hi> clothed with the <hi>Sun,</hi> having a <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>twelve Stars</hi> on her <hi>Head.</hi> Such was the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and the Churches in <hi>Judea,</hi> in the Days of the Apoſtles; And ſuch was the Church at <hi>Rome,</hi> whoſe Faith was Famous throughout the whole World<note n="(c)" place="margin">Rom. 1.7.8.</note> and ſuch alſo were the Churches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> thoſe <hi>golden</hi> Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks <hi>(whilſt Jeſus Chriſt walked in the midſt of them)</hi> and their ſhining Lights, <hi>Like Stars,</hi> the Able Miniſters of the new-Teſtament called <hi>Angels,</hi> whom the Lord Jeſus Chriſt held in his right-hand,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Rev. 1.20, and 2.1.</note> But when the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> departed from the Faith, <hi>as was foretold by the Apoſtle</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1, 2, 3.</note> and Apoſtatiſed both in Doctrine and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and fell away, <hi>as was alſo foretold by the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:94701:10"/>
                  <note n="(f)" place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.1, 2, 3, 4-12.</note> then ſhe became a <hi>falſe</hi> Church, whom Jeſus Chriſt ſhewed unto his Servant John, <hi>in a Viſion and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> like a <hi>Woman,</hi> that is an Harlot, <hi>and the Mother of Harlots,</hi> and calls her the great WHORE<note n="(g)" place="margin">Rev. 17.1, 5.</note> whoſe Name is <hi>Myſtery,</hi> Babylon the great, &amp;c. which is <hi>Papal-Rome, as hath been clearly, and fully Proved.</hi> And I ſhall now prove, and plainly Demonſtrate, this <hi>third</hi> Propoſition,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the Church of Rome is the great Whore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Church which is the Mother of Harlots, <hi>(a)</hi> by Maintaining, Commanding, and Practiſing <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, Whoredoms, and Fornications, is the great Whore: But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Mother of Harlots, which maintaineth, commandeth and practiſeth ſpiritual Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, Whoredoms, and Fornications; Therefore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the great Whore.</p>
               <p>The <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Adultery, whoredom, and fornication of Judah, and Jeruſalem, which God did ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of by his Prophets was their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Image</hi>-worſhip, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4.11, 37. <hi>with their Idols have they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Adultery.</hi> So God complained of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> by his Prophet, <hi>Nahum</hi> 3.4, 5. <hi>Becauſe of the Whoredoms of the well-favoured Harlot,</hi> the <hi>Miſtreſs of Witchcraft, that Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Nations through her Whoredoms, and Families through her Witchcrafts: I will ſhew the Nations thy Nakedneſs, and the Kingdoms thy ſhame.</hi> And ſo did Chriſt ſhew the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Adultery, and <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Papal-Rome</hi> under the Similitude of a Woman whoſe Name is <hi>Myſterie, Babylon the great, the Mother of Harlots, and of the Abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Earth.</hi> God's <hi>great Prohibition</hi> againſt this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Abomination</hi> of <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Whoredom, of making and worſhipping Images in the ſecond Commandement, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.4, 5. And the <hi>grievous</hi> Judgments, which God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt, and inflicted upon the worſhippers of <hi>Idols,</hi> yea againſt them <hi>falſe</hi> Prophets, and any other perſons, that ſhall entice and perſwade any to go after <hi>other Gods,</hi> and ſerve them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, 5, 6, 9, 10, 13, 14, 15. ſheweth us the <hi>ſinfulneſs</hi> of this Sin of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94701:10"/>
Idolatry, And how <hi>greatly</hi> God is provoked unto Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie by it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.20, 21, 22. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20, 21, 22. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 8. <hi>So that Idolatry and falſe Worſhip is ſpiritual Whoredom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let us examine the <hi>ſecond</hi> Propoſition, <hi>to wit,</hi> Whether the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> be guilty of this great Sin of <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Whoredom, Adultery, and Fornication, <hi>(called Idolatry)</hi> and be indeed the Mother of Harlots? The <hi>Ancients</hi> do with one Conſent aſſert, <hi>that Idolatry is an Attributing of divine Honour unto the Creature, which is only due unto God.</hi> And <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> in Epiſt. ad <hi>Epheſ. c. 5. Lect. 3.</hi> Quando bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor ſoli Deo debitus, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibetur Creatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae. <hi>Concil. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi> Seſs. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> out of all the <hi>Fathers</hi> and Ancient Writers concludes ſo, <hi>That is Idolatry (ſaith he) when the Honour, that is only due to God, is given to the Creature.</hi> The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth attribute that divine Honour to the Creature, which is only due to God, For ſhe doth attribute truſt and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in their Prayers to Saints deceaſed, yea to their <hi>feigned</hi> Saints, as plainly appears in the publick Service-Books, Roſaries, Breviaries, Pſalters, and Catechiſms of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">Catechiſ. Roman. Oſorius <hi>tom.</hi> 3. <hi>Concion.</hi> p. 681. Bellarm. <hi>de Sanctor. beat.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 10.</note> The Papiſts praying to Saint <hi>John,</hi> ſay, <hi>Hail, ô holy Apoſtle of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I intreat thee—that thou wouldeſt deliver me, thy unworthy Servant, from all Adverſity, and receive my Soul at the Hour of Death, and wouldſt bring me to life everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> To Saint <hi>George</hi> they pray thus—<hi>He ſave us from our Sins, that we may reſt with the Bleſſed in Heaven.</hi> To Saint <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> ô Eraſmus! <hi>Grant, that by thy Merits and Prayers we may overcome all the ſnares of our Enemies, and be freed from eternal Death.</hi>
                  <note n="(c)" place="margin">Poſſevin. bibl. ſelect. pag. 295. Boz. <hi>de ſig. Eccleſ.</hi> Tom. 2. pag. 200.</note> To <hi>Francis</hi> the Fryer they pray <hi>thus, O Francis— ſingular crucified-Saint, be thou to us the way of Life, make ſatisfaction for us al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, ſhew to Chriſt the marks of thy wounds</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">
                     <p>Exut <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcum</hi> tunica lacero<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> cucul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo: Qui <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus</hi> erat, jam tibi Chriſtus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Franciſci</hi> exuviis (ſi qua licet) indue Chriſtum: Jam <hi>Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> erit, qui modo Chriſtus erat.</p>
                  </note>. This <hi>Fryer Francis</hi> they make equal to Chriſt, as thoſe <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous</hi> Verſes of two ſhameleſs Jeſuites <hi>Turſelline</hi> and <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> do plainly declare. And to the Image <hi>Veronica,</hi> they pray thus, <hi>Haile, holy Face, imprinted on a Clout,</hi>
                  <note n="(e)" place="margin">Chemnit. exam. Concil, Trident. <hi>de Imagin.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Purge us from all Sin within and without,</hi> &amp;c. Thus alſo the Papiſts by the Commandements of Men, <hi>viz.</hi> Popes, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94701:11"/>
Prieſts, yea and general Councils, and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> do worſhip Images, Pictures, Croſſes, Crucifixes, and <hi>Reliques,</hi> which <hi>(they ſay)</hi> are to be worſhipped after the ſame Manner as <hi>Images</hi> are.<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Vaſq.</hi> de a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doratione, lib. <hi>3.</hi> diſ. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> Reliquiae eodem modo at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines ſunt ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randae. <hi>Conci. Trident.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret. de Reliq. Sanct.</note> It's written of <hi>Dunſtan</hi> the Abbot of <hi>Glaſtenbury,</hi> that he bleſſed the right Thumb of <hi>Editha</hi> the Abbeſſe of <hi>Wilton,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found uncorrupted, after all her Body was turned to duſt and aſhes in her Grave, became a Relique.<note n="(g)" place="margin">Guliel. Malmsbur, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Pontif.</hi> Vincent. <hi>li.</hi> 25. <hi>cap.</hi> 33.</note> How many things about our Saviour are turned into Reliques? <hi>viz.</hi> the Manger, his linnen Cloth, his Cradle, his Shirt, the Table on which Chriſt eat his laſt Supper, the Cup wherein he gave his Blood to be drunk, are Reliques to be ſeen at this Day (as the Papiſts and other Pilgrims and Travellers report in ſeveral places and Churches in <hi>Rome, Spain, Ravenna, Piſa,</hi> at <hi>Andegavum,</hi> &amp;c. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is guilty of groſs Idolatry and ſpiritual Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery in Adoring and worſhipping the <hi>Hoſt;</hi> for at the Prieſt's Elevation of the Hoſt <hi>(the Papiſts breaden God)</hi> they all fall down upon their Knees, and worſhip it with very great Devotion, and whoſoever refuſeth ſo to do is counted an <hi>Heretick.</hi>
                  <note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellarm.</hi> de Sacrament. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. l. a. cap. <hi>29. Coſter. Enchir.</hi> de Euchar. Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bric. in Miſſal. Rom.</note> And yet ſome Prieſts have poiſoned the Hoſt, intending to add Murder, yea wilful and Sacrilegious Murder thereby to their groſs Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, as the Monk <hi>Bernhardine,</hi> who poiſoned the Hoſt, to the intent that he might poiſon the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Lucenburgh,</hi> as he alſo did at the Inſtigation of <hi>Robert</hi> King of <hi>Sicily. Baronius</hi>
                  <note n="(l)" place="margin">Cuſpinian. Nauclerus. Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. <hi>&amp;</hi> Baron. Spondan. An. <hi>Eccleſ. an.</hi> 1055. Volateran. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veden. Math. Paris. &amp;c.</note> tells us of a Prieſt that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did, or would have poiſoned Pope <hi>Victor</hi> 2d. at the Sacrament. And <hi>William</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>York</hi> was poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned at the Maſs by his own Chaplins, by that which they put into the Chalice. What can be more Heatheniſh and palpable Idolatry, than to worſhip the Bread con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated by a Prieſt, which is maintained, commanded and Practiſed by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by all her Prieſts and Papiſts?</p>
               <p>Another branch of the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Whoredom and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery of the great Whore, the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is the Adoration and worſhipping the Croſs <hi>it Self, on which
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94701:11"/>
Chriſt ſuffered,</hi> ſay they, alſo the Image of the Croſs and the Sign of the Croſs.<note n="(m)" place="margin">Vaſques <hi>de Adorat. l.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. Bellarm. <hi>de Imagin. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 27, 28, 29. Aquin. <hi>Sum. part.</hi> 3. <hi>art.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Vaſques</hi> the Jeſuit affirmeth, that this is the Doctrine of the <hi>Roman-Church,</hi> and ſo doth <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> and many other great Doctors of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> It is teſtified<note n="(n)" place="margin">Chryſ. <hi>à Viſitat. de virb. Domini</hi> tom. 4. Lib. 6. c. 7.</note> that a <hi>famous Papiſt,</hi> and a <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of Divinity, who dedicated his Book to <hi>Pope Clement</hi> 8th. ſaith thus, <hi>We worſhip the Croſs with the ſame Worſhip wherewith we adore Chriſt himſelf,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Again, Whereas we Aſſerted, <hi>That the Church of Rome is the Mother of Harlots;</hi> for a <hi>full proof</hi> thereof let it be conſidered, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> owns her ſelf to be the <hi>Catholick</hi> and <hi>Mother-Church</hi> of all thoſe Churches in <hi>Italy, Spain, France, Germany,</hi> &amp;c. whether National or Parochial, that receive, believe, and practice her <hi>damnable</hi> Doctrines, and <hi>Idolatrous</hi> worſhip, which are falſe Churches and Harlots: <hi>[with whom the Kings of the Earth have committed Fornication, and the Inhabiters of the Earth have been made drunk with the wine of her Fornication]</hi> and therefore the Church of <hi>Rome (Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal-Babylon as before proved)</hi> is called <hi>the Mother of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots,</hi> Rev. 17.2, 5. <hi>And Abominations of the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hath begotten, born, and nouriſhed all thoſe <hi>National</hi> and <hi>Parochial</hi> Churches, <hi>before-mentioned,</hi> which are called <hi>the Cities of the Nations,</hi> Rev. 16.19. which <hi>National Churches</hi> are Harlots (as <hi>Nineveh</hi> was called, <hi>Nahum</hi> 3.4.) becauſe of the multitude of their <hi>ſpiritual Whoredoms,</hi> and <hi>abominable Idolatries:</hi> whereby it appears, that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Harlots,</hi> for She hath infuſed her <hi>falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi> worſhips, and all her <hi>Idolatries</hi> into thoſe <hi>Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome, (as the Mother of Harlots)</hi> impoſeth her <hi>falſe</hi> Doctrines, <hi>Idolatrous</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and <hi>damnable</hi> Practices upon all thoſe and other <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Churches,</hi> whom She calleth <hi>her Daughters,</hi> own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Authority over them, as being their <hi>Mother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And, <hi>Firſt,</hi> It doth appear that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is the <hi>great</hi> WHORE, by her <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Whoredoms and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94701:12"/>
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4. And the <hi>Woman—had a golden-C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>P in her hand, full of Abominations, and filthineſs of her Fornication.</hi> All kinds of <hi>Idolatry, Image-worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions</hi> in the Service of God is <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Whoredom,<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prid.</hi> de Antichriſto <hi>Lect. 11.</hi> Non in <hi>Babilona</hi> ſolum, ſed in <hi>Sodomam Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, ut non <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> modo Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retricum, ſed (ut habet liber Complutenſis &amp; Regius) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, hoc eſt, Catamitarum &amp; Ganimedum Mater habea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Sic Hep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tades</hi> de Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſto, pag. <hi>99. 129-131. &amp; Doun. Diatr.</hi> de Antichriſto, l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> Etiam <hi>M. Antonius</hi> de Dom. Archiep. <hi>Spalat.</hi> de Rep. Eccleſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi> n. <hi>26.-29. ac Hieron.</hi> adver. <hi>Jovin.</hi> lib. <hi>2,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Marlor</hi> in <hi>Apoc. 18.24.</hi> &amp; in <hi>Apoc. 13.</hi> p. <hi>37. 64, 65.</hi>
                  </note> And ſuch are thoſe <hi>Images,</hi> and <hi>Idols;</hi> thoſe <hi>Croſſes</hi> and <hi>Crucifixes;</hi> thoſe <hi>Pictures,</hi> and painted forms, or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations</hi> of our Saviour Chriſt, of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and of Saints deceaſed, whom the Papiſts ſet up, <hi>fall down</hi> before, and <hi>worſhip.</hi> The Kings of the Earth have committed Fornication <hi>(that is, ſpiritual Whoredom and Adultery) with HER:</hi> And the <hi>Inhabiters of the Earth</hi> have been made drunk <hi>with the Wine of HER Fornication,</hi> Rev. 17.1 2. by <hi>receiving</hi> thoſe <hi>Idolatrous</hi> Doctrines, and by <hi>Practiſing</hi> thoſe <hi>Imaginary</hi> Superſtitions, which the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> Teacheth and practiceth in the Worſhip of God.<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth. 15.7, 8, 9. &amp; Rev. 13.4, 8. Idem,</hi> in <hi>Apoc. 18.</hi> Meretricem Babylonicam, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam nempè <hi>Romanam,</hi> Scortationibus, ad immundiâ Antichriſti <hi>Romani,</hi> Sanguino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentorum ſcil. at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Belluinorum Pontificum, quorum pleri<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Magi, Venefici, Athei, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri,—non Apoſtolici, ſed Apotactici, &amp; Apoſtatici, quales ipſe <hi>Genebrardus</hi> lib. <hi>4. Chronol.</hi> fatetur—Superſtitionum, &amp; Cultuum novorum inventores.</note> 
                  <hi>In vain do they worſhip God (ſaith Chriſt) teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Doctrines the Commandements of Men,</hi> to wit, thoſe <hi>Notoriouſly</hi> known <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Harlots,</hi> namely,<note n="(h)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Doun.</hi> de Antichriſto lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi> Dementatos &amp; mente captos eſſe not at Apoſtolus, <hi>Apoc. 18.23. &amp; 19.2. &amp; 17.2, 4.</hi> qui cum iſta Meretrice ſcortantur, ejuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſcortationibus &amp; Idolola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triis imbuuntur &amp; faſcinantur.</note> Their worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images, <hi>viz.</hi> of Chriſt, and of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> their Invocation, Adoration, and Prayers to dead Saints; And their irrational and ſenſleſs Doctrine of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, Sacrifice, and Adoration of the <hi>Hoſt,</hi> that is, their <hi>Breaden God;</hi> which <hi>(ſay they)</hi> is by <hi>Conſecration</hi> changed into the <hi>very</hi> Body and Blood of Chriſt, which the Papiſts adore, kneel unto, and worſhip, as their God and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
               <p>But beſides the Idolatry, and Superſtition of this part of their Will-worſhip, <hi>let it be conſidered</hi> by the judicious
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:94701:12"/>
and rational <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants, Firſt,</hi> how <hi>irrational</hi> that Doctrine and Practice of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is, <hi>to wit,</hi> of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi> Admit the Sacrament of the Lords Supper be Adminiſtred in the <hi>Roman</hi>-Catholick-Church in a 100. 500 <hi>Places, (as indeed it is)</hi> at the ſame Time, And the Bread be by virtue of each Prieſt's Conſecration changed into the Real Body of Chriſt, then Chriſt hath 100. 500 Real Bodies at one Time, which is abſurd and <hi>irrational. Secondly,</hi> how <hi>ſenſleſs</hi> their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> is; The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teacheth, and the Papiſts <hi>ſenſeleſly</hi> are to believe, That the Bread after <hi>Conſecration</hi> is the very Body of Chriſt. And yet they <hi>that Eat that Bread,</hi> ſee it is Bread, after the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration,</hi> yea they taſte and know it is Bread ſtill, whileſt they are eating of it: And thus they delude their Senſes by a fond and falſe Belief. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> how <hi>damnable</hi> their Doctrine and Practice <hi>of this</hi> part of their <hi>falſe</hi> worſhip of God is, <hi>(viz. Tranſubſtantiation).</hi> The Doctrine is Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable; For the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teacheth her Children, <hi>the Papiſts,</hi> to believe in, to fall down unto, and to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a <hi>breaden-God,</hi> which their Prieſts have made an Idol, with Solemn and Sacred Adoration. And the Practice is alſo damnable; For the Papiſts eating that Bread with a <hi>firm</hi> Belief, that it is not Bread, but the Body of Chriſt, do eat that Bread and drink that Cup <hi>unworthily,</hi> and ſo eat and drink their own damnation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> It appears, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the great Whore; <hi>Becauſe</hi> She is become <hi>the Mother of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots</hi>
                  <note n="(k)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prid.</hi> de mille annis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc. Lect. <hi>13. Roma</hi> eſt <hi>Sodoma ſpiritualiter,</hi> quia ſimilis Sodomae: quâ re ſimilis? foeditate Sodomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticarum libidinum in urbe magnâ horribiliter graſſantium, unde &amp; Mater Scortationum, <hi>Apoc. 17.5.</hi> vocata, &amp;c. Vide jam magnam urbem Papatus; Quid eſt niſi ſcortationum ſpiritualium &amp; corporalium foediſſima Officina? <hi>Petrarcha queritur Ep. 20.</hi> Romae ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra, raptus, inceſtus, adulteria, jam Pontificialis laſciviae ludi ſunt, quod <hi>cecinit</hi> Mantuanus. <hi>Ipudor in villas, ſi non patiantur eaſdem, Et villae vomicas, Roma eſt jam tota Lupanar. Roma, vale, vidi, ſatis eſt vidiſſe; revertar, Cum Leno, Meretrix, Scurra, Cinaedus, ero.</hi> Sic, <hi>Marulus</hi> in Epitaph. Ita <hi>Janus Pannonius,</hi> Etiam <hi>Johannes Sapidus.</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>Lupan</hi> * of Stews, and of all Abominations, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1, 5. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> calls her ſelf <hi>the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:94701:13"/>
Church,</hi> and She teacheth her <hi>Children</hi> (the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts) to believe, that She is the Mother of all <hi>National-Churches,</hi> and whoſoever do not acknowledg Her to be the holy <hi>Catholick-Church,</hi> and ſubmit not to Her <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> Conſtitutions, Doctrines, Diſcipline and Worſhip, are <hi>Hereticks:</hi> All the <hi>National-Churches,</hi> of <hi>Germany, France, Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp;c. are her Harlots; <hi>falſe</hi> Churches, and <hi>Idolatrous</hi> Worſhippers of Images, Croſſes, Crucifixes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before-ſaid.</p>
               <p>The Church at <hi>Rome</hi> was a true Church in the Apoſtles Time, whoſe Faith was famous <hi>throughout the whole World,</hi> Rom. 1.7, 8. But afterwards that Church departed from the Faith, Apoſtatized both in Doctrine, and in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, yea and alſo in Manners.<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                     <hi>J. W.</hi> de ult. <hi>Romae</hi> exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio. pag. <hi>62.</hi> ait, <hi>Joannes 13.</hi> omni <hi>Flagitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> generi, ſcil. Stupris, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulteriis, Ince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtis, aliiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leribus ab ipsâ Adoleſcentia incumbens, <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phenam</hi> Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binam Patris ſui, &amp; duas ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rores vitiavit. <hi>Nicholaus</hi> qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam de <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brach. Erphordienſis</hi> non obſcure innuit ſe à <hi>Martino 2.</hi> velut <hi>Ganymedem</hi> — ad turpiora quaedam expetitum.</note> And ſo became a <hi>falſe Church,</hi> and <hi>a Synagogue of Satan,</hi> and She is now become the <hi>great Whore,</hi> and <hi>Mother of Harlots:</hi> She hath left her <hi>firſt</hi> Husband Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, and hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken another Head and Husband, the <hi>POPE</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> She hath departed from her <hi>firſt Faith,</hi> which was ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Doctrines of Jeſus Chriſt, and his Apoſtles; and now ſhe doth believe the Doctrines of <hi>her holy Father the Pope.</hi> And She is faln from her <hi>firſt Purity</hi> in Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline and Manners, into all manner of Licenciouſneſs and abominable Wickedneſs, and ſo is become <hi>the Mother of Harlots, and of all the Abominations</hi> which are in all falſe Churches, that are her Daughters, whereby the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is plainly manifeſted to be <hi>the great WHORE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It appears, <hi>That the Church of Rome is the great Whore,</hi> by her <hi>barbarous</hi> and <hi>bloody</hi> Perſecutions, and <hi>Murders</hi> added to her Whoredomes, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.24. <hi>For in HER was found the Blood of Prophets, and of Saints, and all that were ſlain upon the Earth. And I ſaw the Woman</hi> (the great Whore, and Mother of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots) <hi>drunken with the blood of the Saints, and with the blood of the Martyrs of Jeſus,</hi> Rev. 17.1, 5, 6. Particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:94701:13"/>
of the <hi>Waldenſes, Albigenſes,</hi> and other.<note n="(m)" place="margin">Abregè Chronol. &amp;c. par le Sieur de <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeray, Pariſ. 1567.</hi> Tom. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>1082. 1086.</hi> ad Annum <hi>1572.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vergerius,</hi> who was well acquainted with the <hi>Romiſh</hi> bloody <hi>Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> tells <hi>us,</hi> that 150000. Proteſtants ſuffered Death in leſs then 30. years. The King of <hi>France</hi> in his Letters to the Pope <hi>boaſteth,</hi> that in the year 1572. (<hi>in the Maſſacre of</hi> Paris <hi>and elſewhere</hi>)<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Thuanus</hi> Hiſt. l. <hi>53.</hi> ad annum <hi>1572.</hi> p. <hi>837.</hi> Edit. <hi>1620. Fam. Strada</hi> de bello Belgico. l. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>373.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Romae <hi>1648.</hi>
                  </note> 70000 <hi>Hereticks</hi> were ſlain in few days, that is 70000 <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were then and there murdered by the Papiſts. And can we forget, or omit, to mention the late <hi>bloody</hi> Butcheries of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> by the <hi>Barbarous</hi> cruel <hi>Iriſh-Papiſts, Anno</hi> 1641. when 100000. were murthered? And if the bloody Invaſion, <hi>Anno</hi> 1588. and the Horrid Gun-powder Treaſon, <hi>Nov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 5th. 1605. <hi>And the bloody traiterous deſign of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Recuſants,</hi> as the King calls it<note n="(o)" place="margin">In his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all <hi>Papiſts</hi> Ten miles from <hi>London,</hi> Octob. 30. 1678.</note> Even <hi>that damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and Helliſh-Plot (as the Parliament voted it) contrived, and carried on by Popiſh Recuſants, for Aſſaſſinating and Murdering the King, and for Subverting the Government, and rooting out, and deſtroying the Proteſtant Religion</hi>
                  <note n="(p)" place="margin">The Votes of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons read to the Lords, and by them alſo approved at a Conference, 1ſt. <hi>Nov.</hi> 1678.</note> had taken Effect, many more Proteſtants in <hi>England</hi> had been <hi>(ere this Day)</hi> murdered and maſſacred by the blood-thirſty-Papiſts. And theſe barbarous, bloody, and damnable Perſecutions and Practices of the Papiſts, are grounded on the very <hi>Doctrine, Religion,</hi> and Faith of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> which is not to be found in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther party of the whole <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world <hi>(ſo called)</hi> beſides. Whereby it is evident, to thoſe that have underſtanding, <hi>That the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is the great bloody Whore,</hi> viz. that <hi>purple</hi> and <hi>ſcarlet</hi> Coloured Whore, the Mother of Harlots and Abominations of the Earth, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.1, 4, 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:94701:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Propoſition IV.</hi> That the Roman-Prieſts are the falſe Prophet.</head>
               <p>BY the Roman-Prieſts, I mean and intend the Pope, the Cardinals, the Jeſuits, and all thoſe Prieſts that do receive Orders of <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ackowledge HER to be the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church, believe Her Doctrines, obey her Canons, and Teach Her damnable <hi>Hereſies.</hi> That the Roman-Prieſts are the <hi>falſe</hi> Prophet doth <hi>plainly</hi> appear by the <hi>falſe</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which they believe, and teach. I call them <hi>the Doctrines of the Church</hi> of Rome, which are approved by the <hi>publick</hi> Authority of that Church by their eſtabliſhed Laws, their Popes Bulls, Decretals, and Conſtitutions, or the Canons of their <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, National,</hi> or general <hi>Councils,</hi> All which are approved and confirmed in their <hi>Trent</hi> Council<note n="(a)" place="margin">Con. Trident. Seſſ. <hi>25.</hi> de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatione, cap. <hi>20.</hi> Praecepit. Sancta Synodus, Sacros Canones, &amp; Concilia ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralia omnia, nec non alias Apoſtolicas San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiones in favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Eccleſiaſt i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum Perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; Liberta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Eccleſiaſticae; &amp; contra ejus Violatores editos, quae Omnia preſenti Decreto innovat, exactè ab omnibus obſervari debere.</note>. And all their Secular Clergy, and all who have Cure of Souls, &amp;c. are ſworn to approve, to profeſs, and teach the ſame— And to <hi>Anathematize,</hi> Reject, and Curſe all contrary opinions and Doctrines.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Vide <hi>Bullam Pii 4.</hi> Super formâ Juramenti Profeſſionis fidei, in calce Seſs. <hi>25.</hi> Concilii Trident. datam Romae. Id. Nov. <hi>1564.</hi> de Reformatione, cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> I ſhall at preſent inſtance in <hi>three</hi> known <hi>Doctrines</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> 1. <hi>The Doctrine of the Popes Supremacy over all Princes, Kings, and Emperours of the Earth.</hi> This pernicious Doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is taught by the Roman-Prieſts<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                     <hi>Blaſius Bagnus</hi> de S. Romanae Eccleſiae dignitatibus, Tract. <hi>7.</hi> pag. <hi>83, 84.85.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Blaſius Bagnus</hi> a Prior <hi>general</hi> tells us, That the Popes Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire is over all the World: and <hi>that HE is the only Vicar of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:94701:14"/>
God, who hath Supreme Power and Rule over all Kings and Princes of the Earth;</hi>
                  <note n="(d)" place="margin">Sic. Simanca Enchir. Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum Tit. <hi>67. §. 12.</hi> p. <hi>349.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twerp. Anno, <hi>1573.</hi> &amp;</note> 
                  <hi>Jacobus Simanca</hi> a Roman-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, whoſe Book is Printed <hi>cum publico Privilegio,</hi> and Commended by the <hi>Cenſor librorum</hi> the learned <hi>Ben. Arias Montanus,</hi> who ſaith, That he had read it—And that it contained nothing offenſive to the <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith. <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> (ſaith <hi>Simanca) are actually deprived of all Dominion and Juriſdiction, and their Subjects freed from their Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and this comprehends Kings and other Lords.</hi> And <hi>Emanuel Sa</hi> a famous <hi>Jeſuite</hi> affirmes<note n="(e)" place="margin">Eman. Sa Aphor. Confeſſ. Verbo Clericus, pag. <hi>41.</hi> Col. <hi>1599.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That if a Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyman Rebel againſt his King, it is no Treaſon, becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Clergy-Men are not the Kings Subjects.</hi> Theſe <hi>falſe</hi> Prophets have taught, and maintained this falſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The Doctrine of Juſtification by works which are (ſay they) meritorious and ſatisfactory.</hi> I need not ſpend Time, and waſt Paper in proving that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and all her Clergy own and teach this Doctrine<note n="(f)" place="margin">Conc. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonienſ. pag. <hi>140. 141.</hi> Becan. Ibid. Concil. Trident. Seſſ. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>6.</hi> Bellarm. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de juſt. cap. <hi>13.</hi> &amp; de Purgot. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi> Rhem. Annot. <hi>2</hi> Tim. <hi>4.8.</hi> &amp; Heb. <hi>6.10.</hi> Greg. de Valen. tom. <hi>3.</hi> diſp. <hi>7.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi> de Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. Bellarm. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi> de Juſtif. &amp; lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>16, 17.</hi> Andradius or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. Explic. Concil. Trident. lib. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> therefore I will <hi>briefly</hi> prove that it is <hi>falſe</hi> Doctrine, whereby it will appear, that the Roman-Prieſts are <hi>falſe</hi> Teachers, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, and <hi>the falſe Prophet.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> gives it <hi>in holy writ</hi> as the <hi>Concluſion</hi> of all Chriſts Apoſtles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Therefore we conclude</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that a man is juſtified by Faith, without the Deeds of the Law.</hi> And Gal. 2.16. <hi>Knowing that a Man is not juſtified by the works of the Law, but by the Faith of Jeſus Chriſt—For by the works of the Law ſhall no fleſh be juſtified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be <hi>objected,</hi> that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> James <hi>ſaith</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That by works a man is Juſtified, and not by Faith only,</hi> Jam. 2.24. and Inſtanceth in <hi>Abraham,</hi> ver. 21. <hi>Was not</hi> Abraham <hi>our Father juſtified by works?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That a mans Perſon is juſtified by Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, and works juſtifie his Faith before Men: And this ſeems to be the Mind of both thoſe Apoſtles; For St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith expreſly <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.2. <hi>If Abraham were juſtified by works, he hath whereof to glory, but not before God.</hi> And St. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of ſhewing our Faith by our works, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Men, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. <hi>I will ſhew thee my Faith by my Works,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:94701:15"/>
And ſo <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> and other of the Ancients uſed to Diſtinguiſh; <hi>Faith</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>juſtifies our Perſons, and good Works juſtifie our Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The Doctrine of the <hi>falſe</hi> worſhip of God, <hi>which conſiſts of many particular Parts,</hi> (that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Practiſeth, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Prieſts <hi>teach</hi>) all which are aſſerted, confirmed, and eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Laws, Canons,</hi> and <hi>general Councils</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> And the <hi>Romiſh Clergy</hi> (by teaching for Doctrines the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Men touching the Worſhip of God<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Joan. Bal. in vitâ</hi> Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. 3d. ſaith that <hi>Innocent</hi> 3d. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that the Words of the Canon of the Maſſe ſhould be held equal to the words of the Goſpel.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Card. Cuſanus</hi> entitleth his Book, <hi>De Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae &amp; Concilii ſupra &amp; contra Scripturam.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Henricus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, <hi>magiſter ſuori palatii Roma ad Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos Bohemicos ſub Felice Papâ, pag</hi> 1447. ſaith, The Pope may Change the holy Goſpel, and may give to the Goſpel, according to the place and time, another Senſe. <hi>Michael, Medina, Gratian, Abb. Panorm. Felinus,</hi> and all the <hi>Roman</hi> Prieſts aſſert and Teach, The Pope may diſpence againſt <hi>jus divinum,</hi> and againſt the New Teſtament.</p>
                  </note> and thereby deceiving and ſeducing them) <hi>are become the falſe Prophet:</hi> like <hi>Thyatira's Jezabel,</hi> Rev. 2.20. <hi>which cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her ſelf a Propheteſs,</hi> viz. The <hi>falſe</hi> Prophets in that Church, who taught and ſeduced the people of God to commit Fornication: ſo the Roman Prieſts do teach them, <hi>that worſhip the Beaſt and his Image,</hi> to worſhip Saints deceaſed, yea to worſhip Idols, Croſſes, Crucifixes, and Images which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath ſet up, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be Adored and Worſhiped; <hi>eſpecially</hi> their <hi>breaden God,</hi> and <hi>Sacrilegious Hoſt,</hi> teaching the People and Seducing them to Believe, <hi>That the ſelf ſame Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who was once in the fulneſs of Time</hi> (and but once) <hi>made of a Woman,</hi> Gal. 4.4. <hi>by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, is every Sacrament Day made of a Wafer by the power of a Romiſh Prieſt.</hi> By all which, and <hi>by ſeveral other falſe Doctrines,</hi> it is plain and evident to thoſe, that have underſtanding in the holy Scriptures of Truth, <hi>That the Roman-Prieſts are the falſe Prophet,</hi> meant and intended by Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13, 14. and 16.13. and 19, 20. As for their Doctrines of Purgatory, Pennances, Pardons, and many other falſe Doctrines taught by the Roman-Prieſts, I paſs by, as not worth mentioning.</p>
               <p>Having thus far unvailed Myſtical-Babylon, <hi>that is Rome</hi>-papal, I ſhall now proceed to Call the People of God
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:94701:15"/>
to come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> fand to forſake Papal-<hi>Rome,</hi> to Renounce the Church o <hi>Rome, as the great Whore and Mother of Harlots,</hi> to Deny the Popes <hi>Imperial</hi> and <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical</hi> Supremacy, <hi>as the Beaſt with his two horns like a Lamb</hi> and not to hear nor hearken unto the Roman-Prieſt, <hi>(that falſe Prophet)</hi> which teach the <hi>falſe</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctriness of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Seduce</hi> the Servants of God. And this Call I give the People of God (<hi>eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in</hi> England) in the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Call to all the People of God to come out of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>REvel. 18.4. <hi>And I heard another voice from Heaven, ſaying, Come out of HER my People, That ye be not Partakers of her Sins, And that ye receive not of her Plagues.</hi> This <hi>Call</hi> is the Call of God our <hi>Saviour</hi> unto all his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in Myſtical-<hi>Babylon (Papal-Rome)</hi> to come out of HER. <hi>Come out of her my People:</hi> which <hi>Call</hi> of Chriſt was given by an <hi>audible</hi> voice, <hi>And I heard another voice from Heaven ſaying,</hi> &amp;c. And this <hi>Call</hi> from Heaven is urged and enforced upon the People of God by two <hi>Cogent</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments or Reaſons, 1. <hi>That ye be not partakers of HER Sins:</hi> 2. <hi>That ye receive not of her Plagues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Two things in this <hi>Call</hi> need <hi>Explanation,</hi> 1. What this voice was? 2. What it is to come out of HER? To both theſe I ſhall ſpeak <hi>briefly,</hi> and then proceed to ſpeak more <hi>largely</hi> of this <hi>Call.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> This voice hath Heaven's Authority, <hi>It was from Heaven,</hi> to wit, the voice of Chriſt in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel <hi>ordinarily,</hi> and by the <hi>powerful</hi> Efficacy of the holy Spirit <hi>alſo,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.5. <hi>For our Goſpel came not unto
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:94701:16"/>
you in Word only, but alſo in Power, and in the holy Spirit, and in much aſſurance.</hi> So had the voice of the Angels of God by whom Chriſt <hi>then</hi> Spake unto his Servant <hi>John,</hi> Rev. 14.6.—13. <hi>with a loud voice,</hi> ver. 7. which St. <hi>John</hi> heard from Heaven, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. And ſo have the voice of the faithful Miniſters of God, by whom Chriſt alſo <hi>now</hi> ſpeaks unto his People, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.16. <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me,</hi> &amp;c. to wit, Heavens Authority.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> To come out of HER, is to Seperate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is <hi>now</hi> become a <hi>falſe</hi> Church, called <hi>the great Whore, and Mother of Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots.</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14.—18. ver. 17. <hi>Wherefore Come out from among them, and be ye Seperate, ſaith the Lord.</hi> The Lord Jeſus Chriſt would have his People to be <hi>Seperated</hi> under the Goſpel <hi>from the unbelieving Jews, and their falſe worſhip (which Chriſt calleth vain worſhip, Matth.</hi> 15.8.9.) And St. <hi>Paul</hi> did Seperate the Diſciples from the Jewiſh <hi>Synagogue</hi> of unbelievers, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.8, 9. <hi>And alſo from Idolatrous Gentiles,</hi> that worſhip Images, <hi>(as the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>doth) and from their Idol-Temples, Churches, and Chappels,</hi> For the <hi>Gentile</hi> Papiſts, and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> their Pope, Cardinals, Jeſuits, and all the Roman-Prieſts do tread under foot the holy City, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.2. <hi>Jeruſalem, viz.</hi> the Church and People of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16, 17. <hi>What agreement hath the Temple of God with Idols? For ye are the Temple of the living God, as God hath ſaid,</hi> Levit. 20.24.26. and 26.12. <hi>I will dwell among them, and walk among them, And I will be their God, and they ſhall be my People: wherefore Come out from among them, and be ye ſeperated ſaith the Lord, and touch not the unclean Thing,</hi> &amp;c. The Papiſts Images, Croſſes, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixes; their Conſecrated Wafers, holy Waters, and Saints Pictures, the Image of the <hi>Virgin-Mary,</hi> and of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour upon the Croſs, <hi>unto which Images the Papiſh Prieſts and people fall down and worſhip;</hi> yea their <hi>Ave Maria,</hi> and prayers to Saints deceaſed, all their holy Bells, Beads, Prayer-Books, and Candles, &amp;c. are all as an unclean thing, and ought to be <hi>ſeperated</hi> from, and not <hi>touched</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:94701:16"/>
by the People of God, whom Chriſt calls upon <hi>with a loud voice</hi> to come out from among them.</p>
               <p>Theſe two particulars explained the <hi>Argument</hi> which Chriſt <hi>urgeth</hi> to <hi>inforce</hi> this his <hi>Call</hi> unto his People fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, <hi>That ye be not Partakers of HER Sins, and that ye receive not of HER Plagues.</hi> As if Chriſt had ſaid, I do by the voice of my faithful Miniſters Call and Command you <hi>my People</hi> to Come out of Myſtical-<hi>Babylon (Papal-Rome)</hi> and to <hi>Separate</hi> your ſelves from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which is fallen, is fallen from her Apoſtolical Purity in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline <hi>or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Government,</hi> and is become an Harlot, a <hi>falſe</hi> Church, the great Whore, the Mother of Harlots, and Abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the Earth, The <hi>Synagogue</hi> of Satan, the <hi>Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of Devils, the <hi>Hold</hi> of every <hi>foul</hi> Spirit, and a <hi>Cage</hi> of every <hi>unclean</hi> and <hi>hateful</hi> Bird. But if you <hi>my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> (as if Chriſt had ſaid) will not obey my voice, nor hear my <hi>Call,</hi> If you will not come out from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſeperate your ſelves from the Papiſts, and leave going to and worſhiping in their Popiſh Temples, Churches, Chappels, and private Cloyſters, Nunneries, Priories, Religious Houſes, Meeting-places, and holy Roods of <hi>Auricular</hi> Confeſſion, &amp;c. <hi>then</hi> in the <hi>firſt</hi> Place you will be <hi>Partakers</hi> of their Sins, <hi>that is,</hi> you will become guilty of their Will-worſhip, and ſpiritual Fornication, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.2. of their Idolatries, Adulteries, Thefts, Murders, &amp;c. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.20, 21. And of their Impenitency added unto their Iniquities. And in the next Place you ſhall <hi>receive</hi> of her Plagues, <hi>Death and Mourning and Famine,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 18.8. <hi>And theſe ſhall drink of the Wine of the Wrath of God, which is poured out without Mixture into the Cup of his Indignation,</hi> Rev. 14.9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
               <p>The Motives and Incouragements I ſhall propound to the People of God to Come out of Myſtical-<hi>Babylon,</hi> and to <hi>Seperate</hi> from the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are theſe, 1. You cannot come to <hi>Sion,</hi> until you come out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Iſa. 35.10. <hi>And the Ranſomed of the Lord ſhall return and come to</hi> Zion <hi>with Songs, and everlaſting joy upon their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:94701:17"/>
heads.</hi> 2. You cannot worſhip God in Spirit and Truth, unleſs you <hi>firſt</hi> ſeperate your ſelves from <hi>falſe</hi> Worſhip and Worſhipers, <hi>John</hi> 4.22, 23, 24. <hi>Ye worſhip ye know not what,—The true worſhipers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and Truth.</hi> 3. You cannot enjoy Communion with God, whilſt you hold a Communion with Idols, and Image-worſhipers 2 Cor. 6.14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>What Communion hath Light with Darkneſs? And what a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement hath the Temple of God with Idols? Wherefore Come out from among them, and be ye Seperate, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider whilſt you continue in <hi>Babylon, (the Church of</hi> Rome) you are under the Guidance of the Pope and Roman-Prieſts, who are ſo far from being <hi>infallible</hi> Guides, <hi>(as they pretend)</hi> that they are erroneous, falſe, and blind Leaders of the <hi>blind</hi> into Perdition; The Roman-Prieſts are thoſe <hi>falſe Teachers, Seducers, Deceivers;</hi> which were foretold by the Apoſtles of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1, 2. and 2 <hi>John</hi> 7. and 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.26. <hi>Theſe things have I written unto you concerning them that Seduce you.</hi> Therefore <hi>look to your ſelves,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>John</hi> 8. verſ. <hi>Beloved (ſaith he)</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Epiſt. of Joh. 4.1, 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Believe not every Spirit, but try the Spirits, whether they be of God, for many falſe Prophets are gone out into the World.</hi> You may do well to <hi>Conſider</hi> alſo, what <hi>Diverſities,</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions</hi> in <hi>Principles, Opinions,</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> in Religion there are <hi>at this Time,</hi> in the World, <hi>eſpecially</hi> among Teachers, <hi>falſe Teachers,</hi> who privately bring in Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Hereſies: And many follow their <hi>pernicious</hi> ways, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1.23. <hi>By Reaſon of whom the WAY of TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH is evil ſpoken of.</hi> Now God hath in great Mercy unto the Souls of his People out of the exceeding Riches of his free Grace, and marvelous loving Kindneſs towards them, <hi>(That they might not be led away with the Errors of the Wicked),</hi> appointed them a threefold Guide, which God hath <hi>plainly</hi> declared in the holy Scripture of Truth to direct, lead and guide his People in the WAY of TRUTH until they come to Heaven: <hi>namely,</hi> 1. His holy Spirit,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:94701:17"/>
2. His written Word, and 3. his faithful Miniſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> God hath given his holy Spirit unto his People, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. To lead them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.14. and guide them into all the Truth, <hi>John</hi> 16.13. and to Teach them all things, <hi>John</hi> 14.26. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.20, 27. And <hi>leaſt</hi> his People ſhould be deceived, deluded, or ſeduced by <hi>Satan</hi>'s tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming himſelf into an <hi>Angel</hi> of Light, or by <hi>falſe</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, deceitful workers, <hi>(who are his Miniſters)</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming themſelves into the Miniſters of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 14, 15. God hath <hi>Secondly</hi> given his People a <hi>Sure</hi> Word, (<hi>his written Word to Guide them,</hi> Pſalm 43.3) 2 Pet. 1.14. Unto which, they do well, if they take heed, <hi>as unto a Light, that ſhineth in a dark place,</hi> &amp;c. And thus God Councelled and Cautioned his People of old by his Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the Law, and to the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony; If they ſpeak not according to that Word, it is, becauſe there is no Light in them.</hi> And the Apoſtle teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. <hi>That all Scripture is given by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, and for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>thirdly,</hi> God hath alſo given his people able <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>New</hi>-Teſtament, not of the letter <hi>only,</hi> but of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.5, 6. and Epheſ. 4.11, 12, 13. <hi>And he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the work of the Miniſtry,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Heb. 13, 7, 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c.</note> And God Set <hi>them</hi> in his Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, 28. to be <hi>Guides</hi> unto his people, <hi>(b) Heb.</hi> 13.7, 17. <hi>Remember your Guides,</hi> ver. 7. <hi>Obey your Guides,</hi> ver. 17. <hi>And ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch for your Souls, as they that muſt give account.</hi> Will any godly wiſe Man or Woman judge in themſelves, that it is ſafe for them to forſake and refuſe this threefold <hi>Sure</hi> Guide of the Spirit, Word, and Miniſtery of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 24.4, 5, 11.23, 24, 25.21. Act. 20.29, 30. 1 Tim. 4.1, 2, 3. 2 Tim. 4.3, 4. 2 Pet. 2.1.2, 3. 1 Joh. 4.1, 2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>which God hath ordained,</hi> and to give up the conduct of their Souls unto <hi>the Church of Rome,</hi> to be guided by her <hi>Laws, Canons, Councels, Popes, Cardinals, Jeſuites,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Roman</hi>-Clergy, <hi>who are blind Guides,</hi> and <hi>Anti-Chriſtian</hi> Miniſters: and ſo to hazard their own <hi>eternal</hi> Salvation? which <hi>falſe</hi> Teachers, and their <hi>falſe</hi> and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:94701:18"/>
Errours, Doctrines, and Practices our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and his holy Apoſtles have forewarned us of in the Scripture of Truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> A Call to the Kings of the Earth to hate the Whore, to make her Deſolate, and to burn her with Fire.</head>
               <p>MY Warrant to give this Call to the Kings of the Earth is that Prophecy, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16. <hi>And the ten Horns, which thou ſaweſt upon the BEAST, theſe ſhall hate the Whore, and ſhall make her deſolate, and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh, and ſhall burn her with Fire.</hi> The ten Horns <hi>are thoſe ten Kings,</hi> which had <hi>formerly</hi> agreed, <hi>and given their Kingdom, Power, and Strength unto the Beaſt,</hi> Rev. 17.12, 13, 17. <hi>until the Words of God ſhall be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</hi> Theſe ten horns are the <hi>Europaean</hi> Kings of <hi>Italy, Spain, Germany, France, England,</hi> &amp;c. who have <hi>formerly</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelves and their Kingdoms unto the BEAST <hi>(the Popes of Rome)</hi> and to the Church of <hi>Rome (that great Whore and Mother of Harlots)</hi> As was <hi>here</hi> fore-<hi>Propheſyed,</hi> and as all <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> have teſtified. But it is the <hi>Revealed</hi> Will of <hi>God recorded</hi> in the <hi>Scripture</hi> of Truth, That the ten Horns ſhall hate the <hi>Whore,</hi> &amp;c. And upon this <hi>Scripture</hi> Ground I take this <hi>humble</hi> bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to give this <hi>CALL</hi> unto the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Europaean</hi> World <hi>to hate the Whore,</hi> &amp;c. And the <hi>Reaſons,</hi> which I ſhall <hi>humbly Propoſe</hi> to them are theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Becauſe</hi> it is the Revealed Will of God that they ſhould <hi>ſo do (in</hi> this <hi>very</hi> Scripture, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.16,) and <hi>They ſhall do ſo.</hi> 2. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</hi> the great Whore <hi>(the Church of Rome)</hi> hath given her <hi>golden</hi> Cup, full of <hi>Abomination</hi> and <hi>filthineſs</hi> of her <hi>Fornication,</hi> into the Hands of the <hi>Kings</hi> of the Earth, and cauſed them to drink, and they and the Inhabitants of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:94701:18"/>
Earth have been made drunk with the Wine of HER Fornication, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1.2, 4. 3. <hi>Becauſe</hi> SHE <hi>(the Church of Rome)</hi> hath Raigned over the Kings of the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.18. Depoſing Emperours, and Kings; putting down one, and ſetting up another, <hi>at the Pope's Pleaſure</hi> (who is HER Head, <hi>Lord,</hi> and Law-giver) <hi>as hath been proved, pag.</hi> 3.10, 11. <hi>of this Treatiſe:</hi> and appears<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Century</hi> 8. Pope <hi>Zachary</hi> depoſed <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> King of <hi>France.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7th, depoſed <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>fourth, Cent.</hi> 11. Pope <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the <hi>third</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth, <hi>Cent.</hi> 12. Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the 4th, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Frederick</hi> 2d. <hi>Century,</hi> 13. Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 2d, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Leo Iſaurus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was againſt Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Baron Annal, ad annum</hi> 730. Num. 5. and <hi>ad annum</hi> 593 Num. 86. and Tom. 8. <hi>ad An. Chriſti,</hi> 593. Num. 86. <hi>Non modo deponi, ſed etiam excommunicari, &amp; in aeterno examine damnari Decrevit. Damnatio &amp; Excommunicatio</hi> Hen. 8. by Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the 3d. <hi>&amp; Elizabethae.</hi> by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the 5th. The Title fixed to the Pope's Bulls.</p>
                  </note> 4. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi> SHE hath ſhed the blood of the Prophets, Saints, and Martyrs of Jeſus, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16, 6, 7. and 17.6. and 18.24. <hi>Therefore Reward her even as ſhe Rewarded you; and double to her double, according to her Work,</hi> Rev. 18.1, 2, 3, 5 6, 7, 8, 20, 21-24. And of all the Nations in <hi>Europe,</hi> no Kings, or Kingdoms have more juſt Cauſe to hate, and to be Avenged on <hi>Myſterie, Babylon the great, the Mother of Harlots, that great WHORE,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and her Head the Pope, <hi>that BEAST,</hi> and the <hi>Roman</hi>-Prieſts, <hi>the falſe Prophet,</hi> than this our Nation, King, and Kingdom; If his Royal Majeſtie, and his <hi>great</hi> Council Aſſembled in Parliament <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> conſider all the Papiſts <hi>former</hi> Plots and <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> againſt the Kings and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom of <hi>England;</hi> but moſt <hi>eſpecially</hi> this late bloody trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous deſign of Popiſh Recuſants, <hi>even this damnable and Helliſh Plot</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">The Votes of the Houſe of Commons approved by the Lords in a Conference, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1. 1678.</note> contrived and ſtill carrying on by them to Aſſaſſinate the King, to ſubvert the Government, and to Root out the Proteſtant Religion, and all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All which I moſt humbly ſubmit to the Wiſdom of the King's Majeſtie and his great Council when Aſſembled in Parliament, for whom I daily pray.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
